<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<content>
	<index>
		<div class="col-md-12">
			<h1>SPARQL Endpoint for British Museum Data</h1>
		</div>
		<div class="col-md-8">
			<div class="section">
				<h3>About these data</h3>
				<p>The data available in this endpoint are derived from an October 2015 dump generated by Matthew Lincoln and uploaded to <a
						href="http://academictorrents.com/details/00422309df7aea69c7475141fa5ec0dcf5862bc3/tech">here</a>. This was a 48GB n-quad file that was
					pre-processed into triples to simplify named graphs into a single, default graph. The data have been imported into <a
						href="https://jena.apache.org/documentation/serving_data/">Apache Fuseki</a> 3.x, a SPARQL 1.1-complaint endpoint that supports the full
					range of property paths, JSON-LD serialization, etc. It is more robust than the original British Museum SPARQL endpoint. At the time the
					export was made by Matthew Lincoln, the data were granted a Creative Commons <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licences/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
						>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</a> license, which is irrevocable for this iteration of the
					data and future derivations.</p>
			</div>
			<div class="section">
				<h3>Future plans</h3>
				<p>The primary goal is the restore functionality of the data in order to facilitate the needs of various digital humanities projects that rely
					on cultural heritage objects in the British Museum. The BM has failed in its institutional obligations (as <a
						href="http://network.icom.museum/fileadmin/user_upload/minisites/cidoc/AGM_2011/LoD_For_Museums%20v1.6.pdf">outlined</a> by ICOM) to the
					general public by <a href="http://numishare.blogspot.com/2018/02/on-stable-uris-at-british-museum.html">pulling the plug</a> on its entire
					URI scheme and its Linked Open Data infrastructure. However, in order to make the data more usable for the purposes of research and
					aggregation, I plan to devise a workflow to transform the data (and this interface) over the course of several iterations:</p>

				<ol>
					<li><strong>Coreferencing of thesauri</strong>. Many concept URIs have already been coreferenced to <a href="https://www.wikidata.org"
							>Wikidata</a>, <a href="http://nomisma.org">Nomisma.org</a>, <a href="https://pleiades.stoa.org">Pleiades Gazetteer of Ancient
							Places</a>, the <a href="http://vocab.getty.edu">Getty vocabularies</a>, etc. The aim is to coreference the British Museum thesaurus
						URIs (which are vital to aggregation projects) and re-insert matching concept URIs back into the RDF in this endpoint. Using APIs
						available from <a href="https://www.geonames.org/">Geonames</a>, Pleiades, or other geographic datasets, we will be able to extract
						coordinates for geographic entities, making it possible to conduct geographic analysis and visualization, a key feature of any cultural
						heritage digital collection.</li>
					<li><strong>Linked.art data model</strong>. The CIDOC-CRM model for British Museum objects was occasionally over-complex in some areas, such
						as production events. The modeling of these data was a one-off implementation for BM data alone. It was an early exemplar of CIDOC-CRM
						in large scale, but the model should be revisited in order to transform it to standards evolving from the <a href="https://linked.art/"
							>linked.art</a> community.</li>
					<li><strong>APIs</strong>. Eventually, search APIs will be built that conform to the linked.art specification. In the mean time,
						coreferencing to Pleiades and other identifiers will enable objects of the ancient world to be incorporated into <a
							href="http://commons.pelagios.org/">Pelagios</a>. It will be possible to generate an API that transorms CIDOC-CRM in the SPARQL
						endpoint directly into the Pelagios annotation RDF model. This has already been <a
							href="https://numishare.blogspot.com/2016/04/nomismaorg-is-now-functioning-pelagios.html">implemented</a> in Nomisma.org and
						Kerameikos.org.</li>
					<li><strong>Improved UI</strong>. It will be possible to improve the user interface for the landing pages for British Museum objects and
						thesaurus concepts, including maps and images (when linked within the RDF data). It is possible to construct a human-readable and usable
						HTML page for objects while still making machine-readable available in a variety of serializations. A HTML page generated from a SPARQL
						endpoint can be more than list a list of RDF properties and literals/URIs. The final extension of UI design might also include
						integration with a Lucene-based search index to facilitate full-text search and faceted browsing.</li>
				</ol>
			</div>
			<div class="section">
				<h3>This framework</h3>
				<p>This framework is a lightweight middleware running in <a href="https://www.orbeon.com/">Orbeon</a> that shields Apache Fuseki from direct
					interaction from users on the web. It is opensource: <a href="https://github.com/ewg118/sparql-ui" title="SPARQL-UI">https://github.com/ewg118/sparql-ui</a>. The data are openly licensed (see terms above). Anyone, including the British Museum
					can freely take and use this application at any time.</p>
			</div>
		</div>
		<div class="col-md-4">
			<div class="highlight">
				<h2>License</h2>
				<a href="http://creativecommons.org/licences/by-nc-sa/4.0/" title="Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)">
					<img src="ui/images/creative-commons-logo_304x106.jpg" alt="CC BY-NC-SA 4.0" style="height:60px;max-width:100%"/>
				</a>
			</div>
			<div class="highlight">
				<h2>Acknowledgments</h2>
				<a href="http://iath.virginia.edu/" title="Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities">
					<img src="ui/images/iath.svg" alt="IATH Logo" style="max-width:100%"/>
				</a>
				<p>This application is on a VM hosted by the <a href="http://iath.virginia.edu/">Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities</a> at the University of Virginia.</p>
			</div>
		</div>
	</index>
</content>
